A Guide to the John Stremlau Papers FA039
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Rockefeller Foundation, 1977-1988; 2; 5.5 Cubic Feet
  - "International Economic Policy: Agenda for Research" - Branson, William H., June 20, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 194)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies, 1981-1986 (Box 17, Folder 195)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies - Conference - "Regional Implications of the Gulf War", June 16-20, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 196)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies - 25th Annual Conference, September 1983 (Box 18, Folder 197)
  - International Legal Studies, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 198)
  - International Peace Academy, 1983-1987 (Box 18, Folder 199)
  - International Peace Academy - "A Proposal to the Rockefeller Foundation for the Support of IPA;s Regional Peacekeeping and Conflict Resolution Project (1984-1986)", January 1984 (Box 18, Folder 200)
  - International Peace Academy - "An Evaluation of the International Peace Academy", September 1984 (Box 18, Folder 201)
    Prepared for the Rockefeller Foundation by Allan E. Goodman.
  - International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War, 1985, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 202)
  - International Relations Program - Budget, 1982-1986 (Box 18, Folder 203)
    Includes some budgetary information on other Rockefeller Foundation programs.
  - International Relations Program - Budget, 1982-1986 (Box 18, Folder 204)
  - International Relations Program - Fellows, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 205)
  - International Relations Program - Statements of Purpose, 1979-1985 (Box 19, Folder 206)
  - International Relations Program - Termination of Program, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 207)
  - International Research and Exchanges Board, 1979-1987 (Box 19, Folder 208)
  - International Research and Exchanges Board - "Foreign Area Research in the National Interest: American and Soviet Perspectives", 1982 (Box 19, Folder 209)
  - International Research and Exchanges Board - "The Role of the Soviet Academy of Sciences in the Soviet Foreign Policy Process and the Impact of Institute Contacts with the U. S.", January 1985 (Box 19, Folder 210)
    Working paper Grant, Stephen.
  - Japan, 1977-1980 (Box 19, Folder 211)
  - Japan Society, 1981-1987 (Box 19, Folder 212)
  - Japan Society - Committees - Committee to Advise on the Future Direction of the Japan Society, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 213)
  - Japan Society - Committees - Subcommittee on Budget and Program, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 214)
  - Japan Society - Committees - Committee on Public Affairs Program, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 215)
  - Jiang Enzhu, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 216)
  - Johnson-Sirleaf, Ellen, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 217)
  - Kettering Foundation, 1986-1988 (Box 20, Folder 218)
  - Kettering Foundation - Dartmouth Conferences - U.S.-Soviet Relations, May 23-25, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 219)
  - Kettering Foundation - Dartmouth Conferences - Talks on Central America and the Caribbean, April 14-15, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 220)
  - Kettering Foundation - Dartmouth Conferences - XV, May 13-17, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 221)
  - Kettering Foundation - Dartmouth Conferences, November 8-15, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 222)
  - Kettering Foundation - Dartmouth Conferences, May 5-7, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 223)
  - Kettering Foundation - Dartmouth Conferences, August 30-September 4, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 224)
  - Kettering Foundation - Dartmouth Conferences, February 15-17, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 225)
  - Kettering Foundation - U.S.-Soviet Task Force on Southern Africa, October 1-2, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 226)
    Summary, list of participants, correspondence.
  - Knowles, John H., 1977 (Box 20, Folder 227)
    Memos of state of Rockefeller Foundation, correspondence.
  - Leeds, Roger - Partnership for African Development, 1982-1987 (Box 20, Folder 228)
  - Lellouche, Pierre, 1980-1982 (Box 20, Folder 229)
  - Lerner, Aleksandr, 1981-1984 (Box 20, Folder 230)
  - Lewis, Flora, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 231)
  - Library, 1984-1986 (Box 20, Folder 232)
  - Lowenthal, Abe, 1981-1984 (Box 20, Folder 233)
  - Lowenthal, Abe - Mexico, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 234)
  - Lyman, Richard, 1982-1988 (Box 21, Folder 235)
  - McManus, Michael, 1984 (Box 21, Folder 236)
  - Middle East, 1984-1986 (Box 21, Folder 237)
  - Miscellaneous, 1981-1987 (Box 21, Folder 238)
    Restricted material.
  - Mossavar-Rahmani, Bijan, 1979, 1982, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 239)
  - National Council for Soviet and East European Research, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 240)
  - Nigeria, 1979-1985 (Box 21, Folder 241)
    Includes Peter Enahoro's "How to be a Nigerian", 1966.
  - Nigeria - House Foreign Affairs Committee - Subcommittee on Africa, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 242)
    Correspondence, John Stremlau testimony.
  - Nigerian-American Relations, 1979-1982 (Box 21, Folder 243)
  - Nigerian-American Relations - Arnold, Millard, 1981-1982 (Box 21, Folder 244)
  - Nishihara, Masashi, 1982-1983 (Box 21, Folder 245)
  - Nolan, Janne, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 246)
    Paper on International Institute for Strategic Studies and Arms Control Association.
  - Officers' and Directors' Manual (Box 21, Folder 247)
  - Owen, David, 1980-1981 (Box 21, Folder 248)
  - Palme Commission, 1980-1981 (Box 22, Folder 249)
  - People (A-Z) (Box 22, Folder 250)
  - People (A-Z) (Box 22, Folder 251)
  - Poland Agriculture Study, 1981-1987 (Box 22, Folder 252)
  - President's Review - Issues and Interests Concerning Women, 1984-1985 (Box 22, Folder 253)
  - Prewitt, Ken, 1985-1987 (Box 22, Folder 254)
  - Program Committee, 1983-1986 (Box 22, Folder 255)
  - Program Guidelines, 1981-1986 (Box 22, Folder 256)
  - Program Seminars, 1986-1987 (Box 22, Folder 257)
  - Rand Corporation, 1982-1983 (Box 22, Folder 258)
  - Rand Corporation - Rand Graduate Institute - Rivlin, Alice M., June 1983 Graduation Speaker - "An Intelligent Politician's Guide to Dealing with Experts" (Box 23, Folder 259)
  - Rand Corporation - System Development Foundation, 1986 (Box 23, Folder 260)
  - "Reagan Economic Recovery Program and the Nonprofit Sector: An Overview and Update" - Salamon, Lester M. and Abramson, Alan J., December 1981 (Box 23, Folder 261)
    Paper, including a list of federal programs in areas of Rockefeller Foundation activity 1981-1982, John Stremlau handwritten notes.
  - Rockefeller, David, 1980-1985 (Box 23, Folder 262)
  - "Rockefeller Foundation", December 3, 1983 (Box 23, Folder 263)
  - Rosa, Karen, 1982-1986 (Box 23, Folder 264)
    Analysis of International Relations program of the Rockefeller Foundation and other foundations, corresopndence, papers.
  - Ryan, Mary, 1983 (Box 23, Folder 265)
  - Sar, Marcin, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 266)
    Rockefeller Foundation fellow.
  - Science and Technology Group Meetings, 1984-1986 (Box 23, Folder 267)
  - Seiler, John, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 268)
  - Sivard, Ruth - "Women: A World Survey", 1985 (Box 23, Folder 269)
  - Social Science Research Council - International Fellowship Program for the Development of Soviet Studies, 1983-1986 (Box 23, Folder 270)
  - Social Science Working Group Meetings, 1983-1984 (Box 23, Folder 271)
  - South Africa, 1986 (Box 23, Folder 272)
  - South Africa - Cold Comfort Farm, 1987-1988 (Box 23, Folder 273)
  - South Africa - Farmelo, Linda, 1985 (Box 23, Folder 274)
  - South Africa - Farmelo, Linda - "Comparative Study of South African and American Race Relations Law and the Potential for Fostering Social Change Through the Legal Process in South Africa", 1984 (Box 23, Folder 275)
  - South Africa - Ford Foundation Study Group, 1984-1987 (Box 24, Folder 276)
  - Southern Africa - "U.S. Study Commission on Southern Africa: an Evaluation for the Rockefeller Foundation" - Baker, Pauline, 1984-1985 (Box 24, Folder 277)
    Correspondence, papers, proposals.
  - Soviet Policy Meeting, November 4-5, 1982 (Box 24, Folder 278)
  - Soviet Policy Meeting, December 1982-January 1983 (Box 24, Folder 279)
    Correspondence, session summaries.
  - Special Interests and Explorations Fund, 1982-1986 (Box 24, Folder 280)
  - Stone, Jeremy, 1981-1982 (Box 24, Folder 281)
  - Stranded Scholars, 1982-1983 (Box 24, Folder 282)
  - "Studies of Western Europe in the United States: Problems and Opportunities" - Treverton, Gregory, November 1984 (Box 24, Folder 283)
  - Task Force on Women's Programming, 1981-1983 (Box 24, Folder 284)
  - Task Force on Women's Programming, 1981-1983 (Box 24, Folder 285)
  - Thailand, 1981-1987 (Box 24, Folder 286)
  - Thompson, W. Scott - U.S.-Soviet Relations, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 287)
  - Trade Policy Project, 1985-1986 (Box 25, Folder 287A)
    Formation of project, requests for papers, papers, meetings, correspondence.
  - Trade Policy Project, 1985-1986 (Box 25, Folder 288)
  - Travel - Moscow, July 9-20, 1979 (Box 25, Folder 289)
    Trip report, correspondence.
  - Travel - China, December 8-21, 1979 (Box 25, Folder 290)
    Trip report.
  - Travel - Poland, May 11-18, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 291)
  - Travel - England, Soviet Union, August 22-31, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 292)
    Itinerary, John Stremlau handwritten notes, clippings.
  - Travel - Japan, China, October 16-November 5, 1983 (Box 25, Folder 293)
    Correspondence, trip report.
  - Travel - Moscow, April 21-23, 1984 (Box 25, Folder 294)
    "Soviet-American Discussions on Southern Africa."
  - Travel - Middle East, January 1986 (Box 25, Folder 295)
  - Travel - Southern Africa, March 1986 (Box 25, Folder 296)
    African Association of Political Science Southern African Regional workshop agenda, Rockefeller Foundation internal report, list of people important in the area.
  - Travel - Japan and the Philippines, September 6-16, 1986 (Box 25, Folder 297)
  - Travel - Africa, Soviet Union, October 22-November 14, 1986 (Box 25, Folder 298)
    Institutes' Directors, October 22-24; South Africa, October 25-31; African Institute of International Economics; Dakar, November 3-5; U.S.-Soviet meeting on Regional Conflict, November 11-14 (Dartmouth meeting); Rockefeller Foundation internal report, background information.
  - Travel Advances, 1983-1986 (Box 26, Folder 299)
  - Travel - Expense Reports, 1982-1986 (Box 26, Folder 300)
  - Trilateral Commission, 1980-1987 (Box 26, Folder 301)
    Correspondence, meetings.
  - Trilateral Commission - Membership (Box 26, Folder 302)
  - Trilateral Commission - Publications, 1984-1987 (Box 26, Folder 303)
  - Trustees Task Force on Development, 1985-1986 (Box 26, Folder 304)
    Includes reports from various Rockefeller Foundation programs, analysis of programs and budgets.
  - Vale, Peter, 1985-1986 (Box 26, Folder 305)
  - Wai, Dunstan - Africa, 1981-1986 (Box 26, Folder 306)
  - Western Alliance Program Development, 1982-1985 (Box 26, Folder 307)
  - Wharton, Clifton, 1984-1985 (Box 27, Folder 308)
  - Willrich, Mason, 1981 (Box 27, Folder 309)
  - Yamamoto, Tadashi, 1980-1986 (Box 27, Folder 310)
  - Yankelovich, Daniel, 1984-1988 (Box 27, Folder 311)
  - Zimbawe, 1981-1987 (Box 27, Folder 312)
- Rockefeller Foundation - Soviet Studies Competition, 1966, 1981-1985 1981-1984; 3; 1 Cubic Feet
  These records document the process by which $2,000,000 was granted to institutions involved with research, training and education in the field of Soviet/U. S. international relations. The records trace the program from the first suggestion in 1981; documentation of previous, current and future interests in the area; the announcement which called for proposals from institutions; the selection committee; the proposals; the evaluations; and the awards. The Rand-UCLA Center for the Study of Soviet International Behavior and the Averell Harriman Institute of Advanced Study of the Soviet Union each received $1,000,000 grants. Both applications are included in the files, with lists of others who applied.
  - American Council of Learned Societies/Academy of Sciences of the USSR - Commission on the Humanities and Social Sciences, October 1981 (Box 27, Folder 313)
    Protocol of the Fourth Meeting and Attachments; "Statement on Advanced Training and Research in International Studies"; Robert E. Ward.
  - Clippings, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 314)
  - Columbia University - Russian Institute, 1966-1977 (Box 27, Folder 315)
  - Harvard University, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 316)
  - "Soviet Influences in the Third World", October 1978 (Box 27, Folder 317)
    John Stremlau paper.
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Applicants, 1982-1983 (Box 27, Folder 318)
    Lists of applicants, correspondence.
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Awards, 1983-1984 (Box 27, Folder 319)
    Grant actions, correspondence.
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 27, Folder 320)
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Foundation Support for Soviet Studies, 1982-1983 (Box 27, Folder 321)
    Rockefeller Foundation Statement of Interest, papers on Rockefeller Fuondation support, other foundations.
  - Soviet Studies Competition - John Stremlau Handwritten Notes (Box 28, Folder 322)
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Proposals - Rand-UCLA Center for the Study of Soviet International Behavior, March 1983 (Box 28, Folder 323)
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Proposals - W. Averell Harriman Institute of Advanced Study of the Soviet Union, 1982-1983 (Box 28, Folder 324)
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Report to the Board of Trustees, September 16, 1983 (Box 28, Folder 325)
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Review Panel, 1983-1984 (Box 28, Folder 326)
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Review Panel - Summaries, 1983 (Box 28, Folder 327)
  - Soviet Studies Competition - Site Visits, 1983 (Box 28, Folder 328)
  - Soviet Union - Center for Foreign Policy Development, 1982, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 329)
    Correspondence, memos, position papers.
  - "Soviet Union and Asia" - Scalapino, Robert A., December 1981 (Box 28, Folder 330)
  - "Study of the USSR and Eastern Europe in the U.S.A.: Structure, Finances, Perspectives" - Gaer, Felice D., 1981 (Box 28, Folder 331)
  - United States - Department of State Grant Program - Soviet-Eastern European Research and Training, 1985 (Box 28, Folder 332)
- Pocantico Project, 1987-1988; 4; 0.5 Cubic Feet
  This series is arranged alphabetically in two folders of correspondence and one folder on travel to Thailand.
  Custodial History
  This material was retained when the remainder of the Pocantico Institute records were offered to Harvard University.
  Appraisal
  This material was kept because it related to the Rockefeller Foundation, yet is not within the same time-frame as the Rockefeller Foundation series.
  - Evans, John - Discussion of Rockefeller Foundation (Box 29, Folder 333)
  - Lyman, Richard, 1987-1988 (Box 29, Folder 334)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1987 (Box 29, Folder 335)
  - Travel - Thailand, May 11-23, 1987 (Box 29, Folder 336)
- John Stremlau photographs, 1061; 0.1 Cubic Feet
  Stremlau, John J.
  - John Stremlau, 1982-1985 (Box 55, Folder 680)